Guide to the China Records Project Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Papers of Individuals: N - Z, Series III
  - White, Mary Culler
    - Typescript articles by MCW: "Miss Nettie Peacock--Brave Soldier of Jesus Christ", "The High Cost of Non-support An incident in medical missions", "Bessie Houser Nunn of Perry, Georgia", "How Bible Teachers' Training School in Nanking, China, came to be" (Box 213, Folder 14)
  - White, Minerva S. Weil (Mrs. John Leslie)
    Biog. info: RCUS Yuanling, Shenchow (1917-1950)
    - Letter incl. autobiographical information, and a picture of MSW, 1972 (Box 213, Folder 15)
    - Pamphlet: "Memoirs of China" (Box 213, Folder 16)
  - White, Ralph and Blanche
    Biog. info: PN, Soochow, Central China Mission 1913-
    - Letters re. appointment of RMW as missionary, 1913 (Box 360, Folder 8)
    - Circular letters and personal reports of Blanche Howard White, 1915-1948 (Box 360, Folder 9-11)
    - Personal reports of RMW, 1915-1940 (Box 360, Folder 12-13)
    - RMW letters to family and re. voyage on Gripsholm, 1941-1964 (Box 360, Folder 14)
    - RMW autobiographical sketch and letter fragment (Box 360, Folder 15)
  - Wiant, Bliss
    Biog. info: MEFB Peking Yenching Univ. (1923-1951)
    - Correspondence: Letters from Bliss Wiant, 1922, 1927-1931, 1948 (Box 218, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Letters from Mildred and Bliss to friends, 1931-1948, 1972 (Box 218, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Letters from the Wiant's family to friends and loved ones, 1923, 1940, 1946 (Box 218, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Letters to Bliss Wiant, 1922, 1927-1931 (Box 218, Folder 4)
    - Printed material incl. music and articles, 1936, 1964 (Box 218, Folder 5)
    - Printed material: "Special Accompaniments to Ten Chinese Tunes from the Hymns of Universal Praise", 1951 (Box 218, Folder 6)
    - Printed material: "The Pagoda: Twenty-five Chinese Songs" fifth and sixth edition, 1967, 1970 (Box 218, Folder 7)
    - Printed material edited by Bliss Wiant: "Hymns of Universal Praise" prepared for the Ohio Council of Churches, 1962-1967 (Box 218, Folder 8)
    - Printed material compiled by BW: "From the Numbered Hymns of the Hymns of Universal Praise", 1964 (Box 218, Folder 9)
    - Printed material: "Four Original Chinese Hymns selected from Hymns of Universal Praise", 1942 (Box 218, Folder 10)
    - Printed material: "Chinese Original hymns", c. 1934 (Box 218, Folder 11)
    - Printed material: "Ten Chinese Indigenous Hymn Anthems from Hymns of Universal Praise"; "Selected Chinese Indigenous Hymns", 1964, 1965 (Box 218, Folder 12)
    - Printed music arranged by BW: "God Became Man", "The Great Commission", "Midnight Sleeping Bethlehem", "The Nestorian Cross with the hymn 'Reverent Highest Heaven Adores'", 1965, 1966 (Box 218, Folder 13)
    - Printed material: " A Chinese Christmas Carol", "Six Authentic Chinese Tunes", "The Upper Room Book of Easter Carols", 1943, 1936, 1959 (Box 218, Folder 14)
    - Typescript Thesis: "Possibilities of Polyphonic Treatment of Chinese Tunes", Boston University, 1936 (Box 218, Folder 15)
    - Printed article by BW: "Oecumenical Hymnology in China" in The International Review of Missions Vol. XXXV, No. 140 pp. 428-433, 1946 (Box 218, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper article by BW: "What Music Means to the Chinese" from The Asian Student Vol. 19 No. 10, 1970 (Box 218, Folder 17)
    - Printed lecture by BW: "Yin Yueh" in The Wheel, 1970 (Box 218, Folder 18)
    - Photographs (copies) ofYenching University Chorus, Yenching University Choir of the Christian Fellowship, 1928 (Box 218, Folder 19)
    - Pamphlet: "History of the Wiant Memorial Residence at Number 63 Yen Nan Yuan (South Compound), Yenching University, Peking", "Worship Resources for the Chinese", 1969 (Box 218, Folder 20)
  - Wight, E. Van Dyke
    - Writings, Chapters 1-6; draft, revised (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
    - Writings, Chapters 7-9; draft, revised (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Notebooks: Lectures - Prof. Alexander (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Notebooks: Notes on Pentateuch - J. Wight (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Personal Items and Memorabilia: "This is your life" (scrapbook), Aug 1895 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Personal Items and Memorabilia: Prints - North China Herald, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Personal Items and Memorabilia: Letter to Wm. Wight, 1856 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Wilcox, Emily C. (Mrs. Floyd C.)
    Biog. info: ABFMS Ningpo, Shanghai Univ. of Shanghai (1913-1927)
    - Photographs of Ningpo Missionaries, 1920 (Box 218, Folder 21)
    - Printed material: American Baptist Missions in China - Excerpt from a published report, mostly on South China, c. 1930 (Box 218, Folder 22)
    - Printed material: "Ningpo Boys School Ningpo, China Commencement Program" (Box 218, Folder 23)
    - Typescript ms.: "The Geography of Ningpo" (Box 218, Folder 24)
    - Newspaper - Shanghai Weekly, University of Shanghai, 1935 (Box 218, Folder 25)
  - Wilder family
    Biog. info: ABCFM Tientsin, Peking, Tungchow, Tehchow (1894-1941)
    - Elec. cop. "Random Jottings" by Gertrude Wilder (Mrs. George), 1959 (Box 218, Folder 31)
    - "Childhood Reminiscences" by G. Durand Wilder (son of Gertrude and George Wilder); photocopies of sample letters and photographs from Wilder papers being compiled by grandson Donald Wilder Menzi, 1926-1933, no date (Box 360, Folder 16)
  - Wiley, Martha
    Biog. info: ABCFM Foochow, Shaowu Foochow College (1900-c.1947) See also: China Missionary Oral History Collection
    - Correspondence from Martha Wiley incl. copies of photographs re. China, 1906 (Box 218, Folder 26)
    - Typescript notes: "Notes Taken During an Interview with Miss Martha Wiley--American Board Missionary, Foochow, China", 1968 (Box 218, Folder 27)
    - Typed material: "Program for memorial service of MW" incl. two of her photos, 1969 (Box 218, Folder 28)
    - Typescript ms.: Biog. essay, "Donald and Catherine Hsueh", by MW (1968-1969) (Box 218, Folder 29)
  - Williams, Maynard Owen
    Biog. info: ABFMS Hangchow (1914-1915)
    - Correspondence to mother, father and folks, 1914-1915 (Box 218, Folder 30)
  - Williams, Melville O.
    Biog. info: From 1929 to 1940 Williams was campus minister and head of the Department of Sociology at Soochow University, located first in Soochow and later in Shanghai. He was active in refugee relief and had responsibility for negotiations with the Japanese on protection of Mission property, 1937-1940. He was Secretary of Missionary Personnel of the Board of Missions of the Methodist Church from 1942 to 1969.
    - Letters to family, incl. travel to China, life in China, 1929 Aug-1937 Sep (Box 354, Folder 1)
    - Letters to family, 1937 Oct-1938 Nov (Box 354, Folder 2)
    - Letters to family, incl. re. return to U.S. due to illness in summer of 1940, 1939 Mar-1940 Jun (Box 354, Folder 3)
    - Letters to family while in U.S. (VA and NJ), 1941 Jan -1945 Dec (Box 354, Folder 4)
    - Writings by MOW: "Work of the MECS 1848-1886" (Methodist Episcopal Church South) (Box 354, Folder 7)
    - By MOW: "Confessions of a Junior Missionary"; "Review of Rethinking Missions"; "Civilian War Relief in Shanghai", 1932-1939 (Box 354, Folder 8)
    - Re. Japanese Invasion of China, incl. "Missionary Involvement in Making Known the Impact of the Japanese Invasion on the Civilian Population"; "Survey Finds Japan's Rule in China Fails", 1937-1991 (Box 354, Folder 9-10)
    - American Information Committee material, incl. "Renovation Manifesto of Chosen Methodist Church; Discussion of Christian Study Group; China Information Bulletins, some by Frank W. Price, 1940, n.d. (Box 354, Folder 11-12)
    - Re. Allen - Lambuth controversy, 1885-1886 (Box 354, Folder 13)
    - Re. Frank Price, incl. biographical information, China Information Service. (See also Japanese invasion material.) (Box 354, Folder 14-15)
    - Re. Miner Searle Bates' manuscript on history of Christianity in China (Box 354, Folder 16-23)
    - "Lessons to be learned from the experiences of Christian missions in China", 1951 (Box 355, Folder 24)
    - Methodist Policy Conference notes, 1952 (Box 355, Folder 25)
    - Methodist mission minutes and comments, 1938 Jan-1940 Nov (Box 355, Folder 26)
    - Biographical information re. MOW (Box 355, Folder 27)
    - Collected material, incl. pamphlet "Japan's Cultural Aggression in China"; material re. McTyeire School, "Southern Methodism in China" by A. P. Parker, 1924-1946 (Box 355, Folder 28-30)
  - Wilson, Robert Ory
    Wilson was a medical doctor at the University of Nanking hospital. See additional correspondence of Wilson in the archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, Series IV.
    - Letter from Wilson to his aunt and uncle describes fall of Nanking and atrocities during Japanese occupation., 1938 Mar 7 (Box 376, Folder 11)
  - Wolfe, Jesse B. and Clara Husted Whiting*
    Biog. info: MEFB Peking Univ. (1909-1912) ABCFM Takuhsien, Shansi (1912-1922) Tientsin, Chihli (1923-1925) Cheloo Univ. Tsinan, Shantung (1928-1935) Peking (1936-1940)
    - Typed ms.: "Our China" (Box 236, Folder 9-14)
  - Wolferz, Louis and Katherine
    - Three circular letters written from Peking, 1926, 1928 (Box 376, Folder 5)
  - Workman, George B.
    Biog. info: MEFB; born 1904 in Arkansas; graduated from Henderson Brown College (1924), Yale Divinity School (1928), Union Theological Seminary (STM, 1939). Served as YMCA Secretary before leaving for China in 1933. Served at Soochow University and later in Changchow in evangelistic work.
    - Correspondence to parents and siblings, incl. re. arrival in China, George's illness with pleurisy, summer vacation in Mokanshan, in Soochow, 1931-1935 (Box 349, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence to parents incl. re. work in Changchow, Japanese bombings (1937), furlough in U.S., daughter's contraction of polio following return to China (1939), return to U.S. for treatment at Warm Springs, GA, 1936-1939 (Box 349, Folder 5-7)
    - Correspondence to/from family, incl. re. return to China, work in Shanghai, teaching at Soochow University Law School; family's evacuation to Manila and return to Shanghai, re. unsettled political situation; preparations to return to U.S., 1946-1950 (Box 349, Folder 8-13)
    - Additional correspondence, incl. letters from Cartwright, Chen, Hanson, Merrill; circular letters of Workman, 1937-1949 (Box 349, Folder 14-16)
    - Collected material related to mission, incl. missionary bulletins, conference program, 1933-1949 (Box 349, Folder 17)
    - Personal items and memorabilia, incl. tickets, programs, Chinese shoes, biographical information (Box 349, Folder 18-20)
  - Worley, Harry Westcott and Zela W.
    Biog. info: MEFB Foochow (1915-1940)
    - Photographs: Christmas dinner Foochow Missionaries and friends, Hwa Nan Student Association, Farewell Service to all the Missionaries given by he Fukien Christian Council, Rotary Club, Foochow, Fukien Union Theological College students and former graduates with their families, wedding and engagement, workers and members on the Foochow District incl. letters to a patron, written by Dr. James H Worley in 1897-8 (James H. Worley was father of Harry W. Worley), 1930s, 1946-1950 (Box 221, Folder 1)
    - Photographs: photos of Bishop Bradford's time (Box 221, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and mimeographed circular letters from Worleys and others, 1931-1955 (Box 221, Folder 3-6)
    - Printed extracts from diaries of HW and ZW, 1941 (Box 221, Folder 7)
    - Typescript mss.: "Notes on Reports of Conferences with Premier Chou En-Lai Regarding the Christian Church in China", 1950 (Box 221, Folder 8)
    - Typescript material re. Methodist Centennial incl. Centennial photograph, pageant for the centennial - "One Hundred years' Planting", official badge of the centennial, 1947-1948 (Box 221, Folder 9-14)
    - Printed material: Handbook for delegates to the second China Central Conference of the Methodist Church Foochow, China, The Foochow Theological Seminary, etc., 1947 (Box 221, Folder 15)
    - Pamphlet re. Anglo-Chinese College, Angli-Chinese High School, 1934 (Box 221, Folder 16)
    - Printed program in Chinese and English, 1947 (Box 221, Folder 17)
    - Book given to Mr. Worley on his 50th birthday by a few Foochow friends, 1936 (Box 221, Folder 18)
    - Typescript material and clippings related to death of Dr. Harry W. Worley (Box 221, Folder 19)
    - Three letters written to Loyd and Beulah Worley from Foochow; two circular letters from Zela Worley, 1947-1950 (Box 221, Folder 20)
  - Wright, Eleanor
    Biog. info: PN Nanking Ginling College (1926-1939)
    - Diaries (3), 1927-1939 (Box 222, Folder 1)
    - Printed memoriam: "Ye Shall Be My Witnesses"; photograph of Theodore and Lela Wright, parents of EW, 1939, n.d. (Box 222, Folder 2)
  - Wright, Elizabeth Curtis*
    Biog. info: YMCA Peking, Shanghai (1919-1948)
    - Booklet: "My Memoirs" incl. a letter re. ECW's death, and 2 postcards (1953-1974, n.d.), 1973, 1974 (Box 222, Folder 3)
  - Wyckoff, Ellen Gertrude and Wyckoff, Helen Grace
    - Book of mounted photographs, Panchuang, Shantung, ca. 1897 (Box 223, Folder 1)
  - Yang, Sherwood
    Chinese educator, associated with North China Christian Rural Service Union
    - Circular letters, report, 1949-1950 (Box 378, Folder 18)
  - Zipf, Elinor J.
    Biog. info: Yuanling, Hunan (1947-1948) Sendai, Japan (1948-1950)
    - Correspondence, primarily to and from Dorothy Nyland, 1947-1951, 1959, 1965 (Box 224, Folder 1-9)
    - Misc. corres. received, 1947-1959, 1965 (Box 224, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Dorothy Nyland, 1947-1949 (Box 224, Folder 11)
    - Typescript writings by ELZ: "Thoughts from the Past", "A China Missionary in Japan", "Why I go to the Mountain", etc., 1949 (Box 224, Folder 12)
    - Slides of Yuanding (Box 224, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified/Miscellaneous donors
    - Misc. general China letters; letter from unidentifed missionary "Eva", 1925, 1949-1951 (Box 307, Folder 1)
    - Printed material: "Vignette of China That Was 1915-1945" by Annie Laurie and Lawrence Todnem, 1974 (Box 307, Folder 2)
    - Book: "The Uplift of China" by Arthur H. Smith, 1907 (Box 307, Folder 3)
    - Typescript material re. stories about China (Box 307, Folder 4)
    - Printed material: Catalogue of the Peiping Institute of Fine Arts, 1934-1935 (Box 307, Folder 5)
    - Typescript material: Communications to missions in China; addresses from 1950, 1946-1947, 1950 (Box 307, Folder 6)
    - Cards: National Pi Yang cards used in China and Taiwan (pre 1949) (Box 307, Folder 7)
    - Collection: Cotton handkerchiefs (Box 307, Folder 8)
    - Photographs re. Canton College (Box 308, Folder 1)
    - Award plates, customs stamps (Box 308, Folder 2)
    - Printed material: New Archaeological Finds in China, Chinese Literature, English Dictionary of Nanking Residents, China: A Sourcebook of Information, 1920, 1936, 1971 (Box 308, Folder 2)
    - Typescript material: China Newsletter of American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1946-1951 (Box 309, Folder 4)
    - Two unidentified photograph albums (Box OV3)
    - Fifteen portraits of Chinese men taken in Hartford, Connecticut, 1881 (Box OV5)
    - Poster: "Portraits of One Hundred Missionaries who left for China during the year 1887 in connection with the China Inland Mission" (Box OV5)
- Oral History Transcripts, Series IV
  - Index / review: List of interview transcripts received as of 15 July 1973; Review of China Missionaries Oral History Project by L. Carrington Goodrich. (Box 225)
  - Ady, Merrill Steele (Box 225)
    Biog. info: PN; Kwangtung,1923-1949; Hong Kong,1950-1965; 3 interviews
  - Allen, Netta (Powell) (Box 225)
    Biog. info: ACM; Nanchang, 1918-1932; Shanghai, 1932-1951; 3 interviews
  - Andrews, John Nevius (Box 225)
    Biog. info: SDA;Szechwan, 1916-1932: 1 Interview
  - Baker, James Chamberlain (Box 225)
    Biog. info.: ME; Shanghai, 1930-1932: 1 interview
  - Bradshaw, Homer Vernon (Box 225)
    Biog. info: PN; Kwangtung, 1928-1940;1948-1951; 2 interviews
  - Cranston, Earl (Box 225)
    Biog. info: ME;,Szechwan, 1920-1928: 3 interviews
  - Cranston, Mary Mildred (Welch) (Box 225)
    Biog. info: ME; Szechwan, 1922-1927: 2 interviews
  - Cross, Rowland McLean (Box 225)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; North China, 1917-1940: 6 interviews
  - Dizney, Helen (Box 225)
    Biog. inf: Cong.; Tiaku, Shensi Province, Shantung: 1 interview
  - Faulkner, Cyril (Box 225)
    Biog. info: CIM; Kiangsi, 1935-1951: 1 interview
  - Fuller, Glenn V. (Box 225)
    Biog. info: ME; North China, 1921-1927; Shanghai, 1936-1941; Szechwan, 1942-1944: 1 interview
  - Goulter, Oswald John (Box 225)
    Biog. info: UCMS.; Anhwei, 1922-1951: 1 interview
  - Hayes, Edward Pearce (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ME; Fukien, 1921-1951: 1 interview
  - Hayes, Egbert McGinnis (Box 226)
    Biog. info: YMCA; Nanking, Shanghai, Nanchang, Peking, 1913-1935: 2 interviews
  - Heininger, Alfred Dixon (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Shantung, 1917-1927; Shansi, 1945-1948: 2 interviews
  - Holleman, Clarence H. (Box 226)
    Biog. info: RCA; Fukien, 1919-1950: 2 interviews
  - Houston, Lyda Suydam (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Fukien, 1924-1950: 2 interviews
  - Hylbert, Ethel (Lacey) (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ABFMS; Shanghai, 1920-1948: 1 interview
  - Ikenberry, Ernest LeRoy (Box 226)
    Biog. info: :YMCA, Church of the Brethren; Shansi, 1922-1951: 1 interview
  - Johnson, Lydia (Box 226)
    Biog. info: YWCA; Peking, Tientsin, Shanghai, 1926-1943: 2 interviews
  - Jones, Francis Price (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ME; Nanking, 1915-1950: 2 interviews
  - Jones, Lucile (Williams) (Box 226)
  - Kellogg, Claude Rupert (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ME; Fukien, 1911-1941: 1 interview
  - Latimer, Mary Lee (Nelson) (Box 226)
    Biog. info: ALM; Honan, 1923-1948: 1 interview
  - Loftus, John Joseph (Box 226)
    Biog. info: RC; Hupeh, 1926-1935: 1 interview
  - McCallum, James Henry (Box 226)
    Biog. info: UCMS.; Nanking, 1921-1951: 1 interview
  - McCormick, Mary Colmcille (Box 226)
    Biog. info: RC, Missionary Sisters of St. Columban; Hupeh, 1919-1939: 1 interview
  - Oliver, Jay Charles (Box 226)
    Biog. info: YMCA; Hangchow, 1917-1934; Shanghai, 1937-1943, 1945-1950: 1 interview
  - Reed, Alice Clara (Box 226)
  - Rowley, Grace May (Box 226)
    Biog. info: PN; Shantung, 1910-1941; Anhwei, 1946-1949: 1 interview
  - Scott, Agnes (Kelly) (Box 227)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Fukien, 1916-1949: 2 interviews
  - Scott, Roderick (Box 227)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Fukien, 1916-1949: 3 interviews
  - Simkin, Margaret (Timberlake) (Box 227)
    Biog. info: West China Union University; Szechwan, 1923-1944: 2 interviews
  - Smythe, Lewis Strong Casey (Box 227)
    Biog. info: UCMS; Nanking, 1928-1951: 3 interviews
  - Smythe, Margaret Lillian (Garrett) (Box 227)
    Biog. info: UCMS; Nanking, 1901-1918, 1928-1951: 2 interviews
  - Stanley, Louise Claire (Hathaway) (Box 227)
    Biog. info:ABCFM; Chihli, 1904-1941: 2 interviews
  - Steurt, Marjorie (Rankin) (Box 227)
    Biog. info: PN; Shantung, 1912-1932; Chihli, 1912-1932: 2 interviews
  - Stockwell, Francis Olin (Box 227)
    Biog. info: ME; Fukien, Szechwan, 1929-1952: 1 interview
  - Tootell, George Thomas (Box 227)
    Biog. info: PN; Hunan, 1913-1949
  - Topping, William Hill (Box 227)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Fukien; 1911-1914, 1918-1950: 1 interview
  - Ward, Katherine Bertha (Boeye) (Box 228)
    Biog. info: ME; Nanking, Chungking, Hong Kong, Taiwan, 1925-1967: 2 interviews
  - Wiley, Martha (Box 228)
    Biog. info: ABCFM; Fukien, 1900-1947: 2 interviews
  - Winance, Joseph Eleutherius (Box 228)
    Biog. info: RC, Benedictine; Szechwan, 1936-1952: 6 interviews
  - Winans, Pearl Beatrice (Fosnot) (Box 228)
    Biog. info: WFMS; Szechwan, 1921-1952: 2 interviews